<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Surely every man walketh in a vain shew: surely they are disquieted in vain he heapeth up riches and knoweth not who shall gather them, Psal.39.6.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5142</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833073</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833073</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2062:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Surely every man walketh in a vain shew: surely they are disquieted in vain he heapeth up riches and knoweth not who shall gather them, Psal.39.6.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1700. And are to be sold unto such who will receive the love of truth that they might be saved.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 29: Richard Stafford.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pride and vanity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37548:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Surely every Man walketh in a vain ſhew: Surely they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted in vain: He heapeth up riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them,</hi> Pſal. 39. 6.</head>
            <p>UPON my inward and moſt retired Thoughts, when I get out from the Hurry, Buſineſs and Company of the World, there doth Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally recur and ariſe to me this Subject of Meditation, of the Vanity of Man. What the holy Ghoſt here ſpeaketh by the Mouth of David, is twice <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought and uſhered in by this Adverb of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, <hi>ſurely,</hi> thereby intimating and giving us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the more we know and conſider of it; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more it doth appear to be ſo, namely, That <hi>Man <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vain,</hi> he <hi>walketh in a vain ſhew, and he is diſquieted <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Margent, oppoſite to the Word, <hi>vain ſhew;</hi> it is an Image. From whence it may be truly thought, that as an Image now differs from the thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is an Image or Repreſentation, ſo Man in this preſent ſtate of things differs from what he will be in the future ſtate of things. Yea, as much as a reality doth exceed and is more than only the Image, Figure, Shew or Repreſentation thereof. So much will Man in the future ſtate of things, exceed Man in this preſent ſtate of things. As it is written <hi>The holy places made with hands are the figures of the true,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37548:2"/> Heb. 9. 24. So it may be believed, and ſo it will be found, that the Heavens and the Earth which now are, yea, the whole viſible Creation and all things contained therein made by the Hands of God, <hi>his handy work,</hi> Pſal. 19. 1. All theſe are the <hi>Figures of the True,</hi> even of which himſelf ſaith, <hi>The new Heavens and the new Earth which I will make,</hi> Iſa. 66. 22. And then all this preſent ſtate of things, is but a Figure of that true future ſtate of things, which God will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring in. So that Man at preſent is but a Figure or ſhew of what Man will be. Somewhat alike to this, the Scripture faith, <hi>It doth not yet appear what we ſhall be, but we know that when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If one had only ſeen the Figure or Shew of a thing, and had never ſeen the real thing whereof it is a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure or Shew, he would not then ſo perfectly apprehend what the real thing it ſelf was, although he might gueſs at, and think concerning it. Hence it is that we are ſo puzzled and at a ſtand concerning futurity. We know not what it is, and yet we have <hi>great thought and ſearching of Heart</hi> concerning it. We ſee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome likeneſs thereof, but not the thing it ſelf. <hi>For we know in part, and we Propheſie in part: For now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly.</hi> And ſo we have ſome faint and imperfect gueſſes before hand concerning futurity, but as to the thing it ſelf, <hi>It doth not yet appear what we ſhall be.</hi> But this we believe, that it will be better and more real than the ſtate we are now in. <hi>That I may cauſe thoſe that love me to inherit ſubſtance,</hi> Prov. 8. 21. And ſo, as much as Subſtance doth exceed Vanity, ſo much will the future ſtate of things exceed the preſent ſtate of things.</p>
            <p>After that <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Wiſeſt of Men, had taken a ſurvey of the whole lower Creation, this is the <hi>Epiphonema</hi> and Burden of his Song, <hi>Vanity and Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit, All is Vanity.</hi> And here in our Text, the Father of <hi>Solomon,</hi> or rather the holy Ghoſt by the Mouth of <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Surely every Man walketh in a</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37548:2"/> 
               <hi>vain ſhew. Every Man,</hi> even the moſt Rich or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous Man, as <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were, for they ſpeak of their own Experience, as well as from the truth as it is in others. Although they <hi>heap up riches,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the following words, which is reckoned the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and moſt Subſtantial end of Life, yet ſtill they <hi>walk in a vain ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word <hi>Walk,</hi> denotes the conſtancy thereof, and that it is ſo for the moſt part, even throughout the courſe of this Life. There is a parallel alike place unto this, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 9. <hi>Surely Men of low degree are vanity, and Men of high degree are a lie, to be laid in the balance they are altogether lighter than vanity.</hi> Which is the moſt diminutive kind of expreſſing it.</p>
            <p>Certain it is, as to the paſt time of our Life, It is all but vanity; for as we conſider throughly and look back upon it, then it all appears as a <hi>Dream when one awaketh,</hi> and almoſt all one as if it had never been. Even the preſent is but juſt perceived and haſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. As to the outward Good or Evil, Pleaſure or Pain we have, it is ſoon over and we are gone. Our Bodies, like brittle Glaſs or withering Hay, can be ſoon broken and daſhed in pieces, and are always Periſhing and Dying. And <hi>we do all fade as a leaf,</hi> Iſa. 64. 6. We are as a Bubble, Shadow or Dream, or by whatever may be conceived the utmoſt vanity of things.</p>
            <p>By vanity is meant what either ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rves to no purpoſe, or elſe ſeems to ſerve to no purpoſe, and in this latter ſence, Man is vanity. For though he was Created to Serve and Glorify God, which is a great and real end; yet many do neglect this, and then they are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and it is fulfilled in ſuch what is written, <hi>Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs Man being in honour abideth not, but is like the Beaſts that periſh,</hi> And who do really anſwer that ſame good end. Yet through the hidden Myſtery of the Kingdom, and alſo becauſe they are converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout unſeen things, they alſo (for the Fleſh is the ſame of a Saint as of a Sinner) ſeem as vanity. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37548:3"/> it is, that ſeparated from God, Man is the meereſt vanity that ever was. <hi>Yet I had planted thee a noble Vine, wholly a right Seed,</hi> (that is, in his relation and tendency unto God his Creator, but if he is one ſeparated from him) then he is <hi>turned into a degenerate Plant of a ſtrange Vine,</hi> Jer. 2. 21. Now a <hi>degenerate Plant</hi> or a <hi>ſtrange Vine,</hi> elſewhere called, <hi>wild Grapes,</hi> Iſa. 5. 4. <hi>A wild Olive Tree,</hi> Rom. 11. 17. All theſe ſerve to no Goodneſs, and bring forth no good Fruit. Even ſo where Man turns away from, and becomes forgetful of God, he alſo ſerves to no Goodneſs or Fruit at all, but is a lump of Fleſh juſt enlivened. A breathing clod of Clay, a Sink and Receptacle of Filth and Flegm, a Seed plot of Stink and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, a walking piece of Earth. Our Text ſaith, <hi>He walketh in a vain ſhew,</hi> or an Image. So he may be ſtiled a vain walking Statue of Earth.</p>
            <p>How ſhould the conſideration of theſe things perſwade Man to <hi>engage his heart to approach unto me, ſaith the Lord?</hi> Jer 30. 21. And for our <hi>Soul to follow hard after him,</hi> and to <hi>cleave unto him. Unto him ſhall the gathering of the People be,</hi> Gen. 49. 10. Even ſo our Spirits ſhould be gathered up and United to the Father of Spirits. This being the way <hi>to live</hi> for ever more, becauſe he liveth we ſhall live alſo.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, if Man ſhould be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from and diſowned by God, he would thereupon become vile, abject and vain. <hi>But now the Lord ſaith, Them that honour me, I will honour, and they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me, ſhall le lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 30. <hi>The Men that have tranſgreſſed againſt me, ſhall be an abhorring unto all fleſh,</hi> Iſa. 66. 24. For he knoweth our Frame, <hi>he remembreth that we are but duſt.</hi> He hath ſo made all Men that as himſelf ſaith, <hi>All their Excellency,</hi> (that is, above the other Creatures) <hi>is of me. The Righteous is more excellent than his Neighbour.</hi> So contrariwiſe, that Man who is <hi>without God in the World:</hi> There is not ſo pitiful and vile a Creature in the World, no not the moſt ugly Toad, as he is: For whereas the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37548:3"/> Beaſts periſh, he ſhall after Death, <hi>riſe up to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhame and contempt,</hi> Dan. 12. 2.</p>
            <p>Our Text is chiefly to be underſtood of the <hi>Natural Man</hi> alienated from the Life of God, and who hath not the knowledge of God. But it cannot be ſo truly ſaid, that the Godly Man is <hi>diſquieted in vain:</hi> For he can and alſo doth caſt his Diſquiet and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row upon God. And he hath that Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that if he heapeth up Riches he knoweth who ſhall gather them, that is to ſay, that is, Beſides <hi>providing for his own and thoſe of his own houſe,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 4. The Poor ſhall gather them both in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and alſo after his Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every Man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi> This is to be underſtood of every Natural and Ungodly Man, as he is buſied only about Earthly things. Certain it is, that the Natural and Ungodly Man doth more walk in a vain ſhew, than the Spiritual and Godly Man doth, for he hath ſome certain propoſed end, and is converſant about real things, even the things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Kingdom of God, whilſt the other is only employed about <hi>vain things, which cannot profit nor deliver, for they are vain.</hi> All this World is but vanity; ſo that all they muſt neceſſarily walk in a vain ſhew, who do not terminate their thoughts and doings beyond this World, who do not in Mind and Heart enter within the vail, where indeed and only is <hi>the ſubſtance of things hoped for. For the Creature was made ſubject to vanity, not willingly, but by reaſon of him who hath ſubjected the ſame in hope,</hi> Rom. 8. 21. From hence it may be truly gathered, that the Creature which is now made ſubject to vanity, <hi>is in hope</hi> to be tranſlated, changed and delivered into a more real and much better ſtate of things. And then Man who now on this Earth walketh in a vain ſhew, will abide (that is to ſay, ſuch who ſhall be <hi>accounted worthy,</hi> Luke 21. 36.) in a glorious and ſubſtantial State. For ſo it ſtands according to the method and appointment of God, that Vanity is in order to Reality, the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37548:4"/> 
               <hi>or</hi> Shew goes before the thing Figured and Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And Perfection is to ſucceed Imperfection, and Mortality will be ſwallowed up of Life, and Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is to follow after this ſtate of Corruption here: And ſo likewiſe Eternity is to ſucceed Time. Thus the Works of God are worthy of himſelf: For as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Remember how ſhort my time is, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou made all Men in vain?</hi> Now if God ſhould have made all Men and all things in vain, this would not have ſeemed (with reverence be it ſpoken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) ſo befitting an alwiſe God, for it is an eſſential part of Wiſdom, not to do things in vain. But when he doth things firſt in a vain ſtate, in order to lead and raiſe them up from thence into a ſubſtantial ſtate, this raiſeth the higheſt admiration of the Wiſdom of the Agent, <hi>O Lord, how glorious are thy works, in Wiſdom haſt thou made them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is now an uſual thing with Artificers or Builders, firſt to draw the Plat-form or Model of what they intend to build and make. In like manner it may be conceived, that he who built all things (now he who built all things, is God) did create the Heavens and the Earth and all the things that therein are, as a Plat-form or Model of the <hi>new Heavens and the new Earth</hi> which he will make.</p>
            <p>If we could now have ſuch lively Thoughts and Apprehenſions of the new Heavens and new Earth and of the things contained therein, as we ſhall then have a ſence and feeling and open ſight thereof in the future ſtate, all one as we now have of the things in this preſent ſtate, then by reaſon of the ſo much exceeding Greatneſs, Duration and Reality of thoſe future things, we ſhould be otherwiſe affected and concerned as to them, then now we are. Even whilſt our Body is on this Earth, <hi>our Converſation would be in Heaven,</hi> and our Mind would be always there. And like as Strangers and Pilgrims when they are from <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome in another Country, their mind runs ſtill or for the moſt part on home, even whilſt they are in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37548:4"/> ſtrange and diſtant place. In like manner if we did <hi>confeſs our ſelves to be Pilgrims and Strangers on the Earth,</hi> Heb. 11. 13. Our Thoughts, Mind and Deſire would be wholly taken up about Heaven and Futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Who then much minds the Figure or Picture, when he hath before him the thing Figured or Pictured? Then it will appear, that the things which are now viſible, are as the Figure or Shew; and only what things are now inviſible, they are the Realities: <hi>While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen, for the things which are ſeen are Temporal, but the things which are not ſeen, are Eternal.</hi> It may now be ſo brought to paſs by the <hi>Word of Faith which we Preach,</hi> which ſpeaketh of <hi>thoſe things that be not as though they were,</hi> and <hi>warns of things not ſeen as yet</hi> Heb. 11. 7. That the things which now are not ſeen, might be rendred intelligible unto our Souls, all one as the things now ſenſible are to our outward ſenſes. But People are ſo ſettled on the lees and ſunk down and immerſed into ſenſuality and the cares and concernments of this Life, that they are not altogether ſo much and ſo continually thoughtful about the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they ſhould be. Here again our Duty to God and care for our Immortal Soul teaches, rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce things preſent as much as poſſible, that we may think and act more after the things to come. It is Sin and Senſuality that do now eclipſe, overſhadow as with a Cloud and darken the Soul, and hinders from the ſight and light of the ſuture eternal things. Although we do Daily, yea every Hour and Minute preſs nearer and nearer unto them. The more we think of thoſe ſuture eternal things, the more we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the vanity and littleneſs of all preſent things. Theſe are now heightned in expectation and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but when we know the utmoſt of them, then they do clearly appear to be vain. They are not only vain, but alſo they ſoon paſs away; ſo that the vanity is alſo infolded in the tranſitorineſs of them. It they were real and ſubſtantial good things, yet they ought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37548:5"/> not to be much eſteemed or ſought after, becauſe they do ſoon paſs away and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>Hence doth appear forth the truth of the following words, <hi>Surely they are diſquieted in vain:</hi> For People are diſquieted about things which properly ſhould not diſquiet them at all; and alſo the matter and cauſe of their grief ſo ſoon paſſeth away, that upon this account it ſhould not diſquiet them. All Sorrow and Diſquiet ſhould be indeed turned into Sorrow and Diſquiet for Sin. We ſhould <hi>walk ſoftly all</hi> the reſidue of <hi>our Years in the bitterneſs of our Soul,</hi> becauſe we have ſinned againſt the Lord, the <hi>Habitation of Juſtice,</hi> the <hi>Hope of our Fathers,</hi> and this only would not be to be diſquieted in vain, according to what is written, <hi>Now I rejoyce, not that ye were made ſorry but that ye ſorrowed to repentance: for ye were made ſorry after a godly manner, that ye might receive damage by us in nothing. For godly ſorrow worketh repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to ſalvation not to be repented of: but the ſorrow of the world worketh death. For behold this ſelf-ſame thing that ye ſorrowed after a godly ſort, what carefulneſs it wrought in you, yea, what clearing of your ſelves, yea, what indignation, yea, what fear, yea, what vehement deſire, yea, what zeal, yea, what revenge: in all things ye have approved your ſelves to be clear in this matter,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. From all which it appears that Godly Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or ſuch Sorrow which ariſes towards God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of having ſinned againſt him, is not Sorrow or Diſquiet in vain; for it produces all theſe real good Effects aforementioned. But the Apoſtle there ſaith, <hi>The ſorrow of the world worketh death.</hi> So all Sorrow which ariſes meerly from the things of this World, is to be diſquieted in vain. As it is elſewhere writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Notwithſtanding in this rejoyce not, that the Spirits are ſubject unto you, but rather rejoyce becauſe your names are written in Heaven.</hi> So this ſhould be the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard and meaſure of all our Sorrow and Vexation; to be ſorry or vexed only for ſuch things which hinder our going and entrance into Heaven; and that is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37548:5"/> Sin committed, or Sin remaining unpardoned, or the oppoſitions temptations and hindrances of Satan. Hear what Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Let not your heart be troubled, ye believe in God; believe alſo in me.</hi> So let not thy Soul be vexed or <hi>diſquieted within thee;</hi> altho' thou art in Priſon or Poverty, or in pining Sickneſs, or near to Death it ſelf: For all theſe put together cannot make thee utterly miſerable, unleſs God hath forſaken thee, and withdrawn his Mercy and Loving-kindneſs from thee. But be thou troubled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted in good earneſt, <hi>Weep and Howl for your miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that ſhall come upon you,</hi> If thou art in a ſtate of Sin, and it <hi>hath dominion over thee;</hi> for this will really conſign thee over and ſink down into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Puniſhment. All our rejoycing and diſquiet ſhould hence be, according as we apprehend from true ſigns and evidences whether God be in favour or <hi>is diſpleaſed,</hi> Iſa. 59. 15. with us. As aforementioned, Man and all things ſeperated from God, is the meereſt and utmoſt vanity: So here if it was not in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to God, there is nothing in all the World, worthy to be diſquieted about, no more than it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Man to groan or cry for the ſcratching of a Pin. In truth, conſidering the perpetual Flux of time, which is always carrying and forcing us off from the Stage of this Earth, however we take it in good or evil part, whether we are pleaſed or diſpleaſed thereat, yet away we muſt: So that it is not much matter in which of the two tempers of Mirth or Sorrow, Contentment or Vexation we are in. But this ought to be moſt mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cared for, whether we Sin or not, and how much good we do; for this is not to be concerned or diſquieted in vain, in that it doth tend to realities in the end. <hi>They that have done good, ſhall come forth to the Reſurrection of Life; and they that have done evil, to the Reſurrection of Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore Brethren, <hi>give all diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure.</hi> Heaven is ſo exceeding and eternal a good, that it can never be made too ſure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37548:6"/> off. Here as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>In the multitude of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors there is ſafety,</hi> holds true in things pertaining to future and endleſs Life, all one as in things of this preſent Life. In the multitude of Godly Books and Sermons there is ſafety in order to inſtruct or exhort or put in mind of any thing to make ſure of that bleſſed Place. The Wiſdom of God hath ſaid and ordained, <hi>For precept muſt be upon precept, precept upon precept, line upon line, line upon line, here a little and there a little,</hi> Iſa. 28. 10. And as the Scriptures were given by inſpiration of God to make us Wiſe unto Salvation, ſo every thing which is truly opened and alledged from thence (as I do this day in what I write and publiſh unto the World) doth alſo pertain and help to the ſame great and good end.</p>
            <p>But this is one difference between the formal Worſhipper and the real Chriſtian. The firſt thinks it an eaſie thing to make ſure of Heaven, and that it is preſently done; like <hi>Saul</hi> who did ſay to <hi>Samuel, Bleſſed art thou of the Lord, I have performed<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord,</hi> So ſuch are apt to flatter and deceive their own Souls, as if they were fit for Heaven. And like the Young Man in the Goſpel. <hi>All theſe have I kept from my youth up, what lack I yet?</hi> As to both of which the anſwer of God by his Son and Prophet doth point out ſomewhat further and more to be done. <hi>What meaneth then this bleating of the Sheep in mine ears, and the lowing of the Oxen which I hear?</hi> What mean thoſe unmortified Sins and carnal Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Luſtings after evil things? And ſo it ye were indeed perfect and fit for Heaven, <hi>ye would ſell all that ye had and give to the poor:</hi> Ye would part with all the Guilt and Corruption that is in your Nature, not only the actual breakings forth of Sin, but even the inclinations and tendences to Sin or Evil; for as long as there remain any of them in the Body, in the Sight and Acceptation of God, ye are not fit for Heaven. <hi>For fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God; neither ſhall in any wiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37548:6"/> 
               <hi>into it any thing that defileth.</hi> As long as we are on this Earth, which is the place of warfare and waiting, No people are abſolutely fit for Heaven; but ſtill there is ſomewhat more and further to be done for it. As long as we have time, ſo there is <hi>ſpace</hi> given us <hi>for Repentance,</hi> Rev. 2. 21. And to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it yet better and better, <hi>to perfect our works,</hi> Rev. 3. 2. Yet more and more, that they may ſhine unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Day, even till the breaking forth of the Day of Immortality. As long as we are on this Corrupt Earth, and ſinful ſinning Body, we are never holy enough to meet with and appear before the holy God, but ſtill as long as we have life and being, ſo ought we to be ſtill a doing according to the Exhortation which ſpeaketh on this wiſe, <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes (dearly beloved) let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God. Bleſſed are the pure in heart for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> So we are ſtill to be upon the cleanſing and purifying Work, according to what is commanded, <hi>Waſh ye, Make ye clean.</hi> So is the mind and endeavour of the true Servants of God, even of the Elect and ſuch that ſhall Obtain, <hi>Unto which promiſe our twelve Tribes inſtantly ſerving God day and night hope to come,</hi> Acts 26. 7. <hi>Thy God whom thou ſerveſt continually,</hi> Dan. 6. 16. Without more intermiſſion or wearineſs than what is neceſſary; ſuch Service hath the favour and acceptance of God. And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect, I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt Jeſus. Brethren I count not my ſelf to have apprehended</hi> (and ſo he did not think himſelf fit for Heaven) <hi>but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things that are behind, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before.</hi> This Bleſſed Saint did take more pains for Heaven than any Chriſtians now a Days, and much leſs formal Worſhippers can pretend unto. He ſaith thus of himſelf, That <hi>three Years he did not ceaſe to warn every one night and day</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37548:7"/> 
               <hi>with Tears.</hi> The conſideration whereof is ſaid to have made <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (who was alſo a labourer and not a loyterer in God's Harveſt as is the manner of too many in theſe days) to tremble becauſe of his own remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and negligence in the Work of the Miniſtry compared with that. The ſame Apoſtle was in <hi>labours more abundant, in watchings, in faſtings, in impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and tumults.</hi> Truly and in good earneſt, all that ever a poor Mortal Creature can do, putting forth all his ſtrength, imploying all his time, uſing and exerting all that is within and without him, is little enough to obtain Heaven.</p>
            <p>If it were not for this real and great end, all Men's doings are in vain: For nothing remains in a Man but what he doth in the Service of God, and for the good of his own Soul. <hi>The world paſſeth away and the luſt thereof, but he that doth the will of God, abideth for ever.</hi> All other Acts and Actions periſh in the uſing, and at length come to an utter end, and ſignifie nothing at laſt. It is to be diſquieted in vain, and to be cumbred about many things in vain, and for <hi>the people to labour in the very fire, and to weary thmeſelves for very vanity,</hi> Heb. 2. 13. And whereas the Prophet doth before ask the queſtion, <hi>Is it not of the Lord of Hoſts</hi> that people do thus? Thereby is imported forth, that the Lord doth leave them and withdraw himſelf from them, and then they do labour in the very Fire, and weary themſelves for very vanity: Which confirms what was aforeſaid; that although Man indeed is a noble Creature, <hi>wholly a right Seed,</hi> conſidered in his Relation to God, yet ſeparated from and forſaken by God, he is the meereſt vanity that can be. <hi>Surely every Man walketh in a vain ſhew: Surely they are diſquieted in vain: He heapeth up riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is ſaid in the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> that upon the Death of a Man, <hi>his Sons come to honour and he knoweth it not.</hi> So we may give a gueſs how things will be after our Deceaſe, all one as we may of the time to come
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37548:7"/> whilſt we are in Life (The like hath been fulfilled in our Brethren of the ſame Condition, Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Years) yet we know not exactly how it will be. As to our own forecaſts concerning futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, moſt commonly it happens contrary, but always otherwiſe than we think, or imagine before hand. Foreknowledge is the pecular Attribute of God who knoweth all things: But it is not for us Creatures to know the things to come. But we have heard with our Ears, and our Fathers have told us, and we have read of ſeveral Examples of thoſe who have heaped up Riches and knew not who ſhould gather them. For after that they have been Dead, it may be their greateſt Enemies, and thoſe whom they whilſt living would not ſpeak a good and kind word unto, nor give them ſo much as a Cup of cold Water; and yet either by being next of Kin the right of Inheritance did devolve unto them, or by the contention and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the Law, ſome way or other it hath fallen unto them. There is ſomewhat alike to this ſaid in <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>The ground of a certain rich Man brought forth plentifully. And he thought within himſelf, ſaying, What ſhall I do becauſe I have no room where to beſtow my fruits, And he ſaid, this will I do, I will pull down my barns and build greater, there will I beſtow all my fruits and my goods. And I will ſay to my Soul, Soul, thou haſt much goods laid up for many years, Take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry. And God ſaid unto him, thou fool, this night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee: Then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided? So is he that layeth up treaſure for himſelf, and is not rich towards God.</hi> Whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided? And ſo he heapeth up Riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them. They come near to the ſame ſenſe and ſignification. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that thoſe things which he hath provided, and the Riches he hath heaped up, are no longer his when once his Soul is required of him; and then he knoweth not who ſhall gather them. And whereas that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37548:8"/> and uſeful Truth is afterwards added, <hi>So is he that layeth up treaſure for himſelf and is not rich towards God.</hi> From all this laid and conſidered together, it appears that the <hi>heaping up riches</hi> (which ſignifies the abundance, plenty and ſuperfluities of them) is not the proper end of Life. Indeed every one ought to be honeſt and diligent in his Calling, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his own Houſe. But ſaith the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Take heed and beware of Covetouſneſs, for a Man's life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth.</hi> So if a Man can have the neceſſaries and comforts of Life, by doing that (and that only) which is <hi>Lawful and Right,</hi> to ſuch the promiſe is, <hi>His Soul ſhall live.</hi> If he can bring the World about and pay every one his own. If he hath <hi>neither poverty nor riches,</hi> but is <hi>fed with food convenient for him,</hi> Such an one whilſt he fears and ſerves God and <hi>fulfils all righteouſneſs,</hi> ſhall be more happy and bleſſed in the end, than he that heapeth up Riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them, or than he that lays up goods for many Years and is not rich towards God.</p>
            <p>The reaſon and end of things is to be conſidered. Wherefore is it that any one deſires Riches? If he be one who loves God with all <hi>his Heart, and with all his Strength, and with all his Soul, and with all his Mind</hi> and who underſtands throughly the things pertaining to his Kingdom. Then it is, becauſe he would <hi>Honour the Lord with his Subſtance,</hi> becauſe he would approve himſelf as <hi>a good Steward of the manifold gifts of God.</hi> For ſo much as we have, ſo much we are accountable for. <hi>Let him that ſtole, ſteal no more, but rather let him labour, working with his hands the thing which is good, that he may have to give to him that need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> Eph. 4. 28. Hence it appears, that even in the labour of our Hands which is to ſubminiſter the neceſſaries of Life, ſomewhat out of that ſhould be afforded to Alms and good Works: Much more a larger Portion ſhould be expended towards the ſame end out of the Plenty and Superfluities of Life. Yea, whatever
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37548:8"/> is more than the neceſſity and conveniencies of each Family, the ſame belongeth to the Poor, and is their due. Whereupon <hi>ſhewing mercy to the Poor</hi> is called <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> Dan. 4. 27. The more Riches or Money any one hath committed unto him in this Life, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably a demand and account will be required of him at the Day of Judgment, whether he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended accordingly for the relief of the Poor, and for the <hi>maintenance of good works,</hi> Titus 3. 8. As it is written, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give an account.</hi> So it may be truly ſaid to every one who hath, or to whom this Worlds Goods are committed, do thou ſo uſe, expend and diſtribute them forth, as thou that muſt give account thereof. That time will come, even upon the Death of each one, <hi>Give an account of thy Stewardſhip, for thou mayeſt be no longer Steward.</hi> And it being afterwards commanded, <hi>And I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Make to your ſelves friends of the mammon of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, that when ye fail, they may receive you into everlaſting habitations.</hi> For we <hi>brought nothing into this World, and it is certain that we can carry nothing out.</hi> So in the Day of our Death, and from thence forward throughout all eternity, we ſhall have no benefit of our Money or the Riches we had in this Life, but of what we gave to the Poor, or diſtributed towards the maintenance of good Works.</p>
            <p>For my part, as I have a God to ſerve and a Soul to have (which I deſire as much to have ſaved as any Man living) In that little Money which falls into my hands, <hi>(for the World hateth me, becauſe I teſtifie of it that the works thereof are evil. If ye were of the World, the World would love his own)</hi> Beſides the neceſſaries of Life provided for, the ſame is the conſtant thought of my Heart, and endeavour of my Hands, ſo to expend the greater part thereof, as that I muſt give account thereof before God, and ſo that I may give up a good account of my Stewardſhip, and that it may be moſt acceptable and pleaſing in the ſight of the Lord,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37548:9"/> and that I may <hi>receive a full reward,</hi> 2. John 8. Even the Reward of ſuch who have done the beſt works.</p>
            <p>Now of good Works there is a twofold ſort, either outward Alms which is a temporal kindneſs to the dying Body. And ſeeing that we <hi>have this treaſure in Earthen Ueſſels,</hi> and by the good health and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Body, we are better enabled to ſerve God, and to follow the Duties of our reſpective Callings. And they would Languiſh, Sicken and Die without neceſſary Food and Rayment: So that the Subminiſtring of theſe to the Perſon who really wants them is a very great good, in that it doth <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Life.</hi> But yet as the Apſtle ſaith, <hi>Covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, and yet ſhew I to you a more excellent way,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 31. As much as the Soul is better and a more enduring Subſtance than the Body, ſo what doth good immediately unto the Soul, is proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably a better Work, than what is a temporal kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto the dying Body. Hereupon the words of eternal Life, are better than Money or Food, for the former are all one neceſſary to the feeding and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the Soul unto eternal Life, all one as Meat and Drink are neceſſary unto temporal Life. According to what <hi>David</hi> ſaith by the Spirit, which ſame Spirit gave him the Faith and Knowledge of the future and inviſible things of God, <hi>The Law of thy mouth is better unto me then thouſands of Gold and Silver,</hi> Pſal. 119. 72. So that the <hi>making known thy Truth,</hi> Iſa. 38. 19. Or the words of eternal Life, and the multiplying the Copies thereof, is conſequently the Beſt of works, as much as the Soul is better than the Body.</p>
            <p>Indeed in this ignorant, but more eſpecially Corrupt World (where we <hi>know in part)</hi> things do appear dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently unto Chriſtians, although they all pretend to walk by the ſame Rule of the Scriptures. Yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as many called Chriſtians, <hi>(who ſeem to be Religious</hi> and to make a fair ſhew in the Fleſh) have a ſecret inward enmity againſt Publiſhing the Word
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37548:9"/> and Truth of God, for the ſame and alike Reaſons, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did take Counſel to put Chriſt to Death, <hi>Becauſe they perceived that he had ſpoken the Parable againſt them.</hi> Even ſo ſuch apprehend, that the Word Spoken or Publiſhed is againſt ſome of their own ſinful, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt or Hypocritical doings; therefore they conceive beforehand an enmity towards, and afterwards an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or Perſecution againſt it, and <hi>They do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Love of the Truth,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2. 10. Nor will they do any thing for it. But for my part though I cannot as yet ſo fully ſay as I could wiſh for, that I have made my Heart clean, nor have all my doings as yet been perfectly conformable to that great and compleat Rule of Righteouſneſs in Scripture, <hi>For in many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all.</hi> And the Scripture is againſt ſome of my doings: which I deſire to ceaſe from once before I die, and to bring them all, yea every Word and Thought in me unto a conformity and agreeableneſs unto all the Words of God's Law; for I believe and tremble, that <hi>The Wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighteouſneſs of Men.</hi> Which word <hi>Unrighteouſneſs</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies what is a variation from the great Rule of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs aforementioned. Yet nevertheleſs I am ſo far from conceiving an Enmity, Oppoſition, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt that <hi>form of ſound words</hi> in Scripture or any of them, that <hi>I can do nothing againſt the Truth,</hi> but for the Truth. And conſidering in my Mind the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding preciouſneſs and neceſſity of the Truth in order to bring others and my ſelf unto eternal Life, (it being equally neceſſary for that end, as Meat and Drink to keep and preſerve temporal Life; as eternal Life is much beyond and better than this preſent temporal Life, yea more then Ten Thouſand fold, here to allude unto thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Yet I had rather ſpeak five words with my underſtanding, that by my voice I might teach others alſo, than ten thouſand words in an unknown tongue.</hi> In like manner if I had ſo much Money, I had rather beſtow five Pounds towards the Publiſhing of God's eternal Truth, which is to feed up the Soul
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37548:10"/> unto eternal Life, then Ten Thouſand Pounds to feed the Poor, that is, to feed their Bodies only. Or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I had wherewithal and I did beſtow five Pounds towards the Publiſhing of God's eternal Truth, and alſo I did indeed beſtow Ten Thouſand Pounds to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards feeding of the Poor; yet I ſhould have more expectation of a better Reward from God for the five Pounds expended that way, than from the Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds diſtributed the other way; becauſe of the ſo much more Excellency and Preciouſneſs of <hi>Truth,</hi> which is for the <hi>ſaving of the Soul,</hi> over outward Alms which is only for feeding of the Body.</p>
            <p>It is the Command of God, <hi>Buy the Truth and ſell it not, alſo Wiſdom, Inſtruction, and Underſtanding.</hi> For ſhould not People lay out their Money to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſaving of their Souls as the Truth doth? Yet contrariwiſe People do day after day buy Meat and Drink to feed their Bodies, but they grudge and will not lay out their Money for ſuch Books wherein are contained the <hi>Words of Truth,</hi> which are requiſite and neceſſary to feed up the Soul unto eternal Life, and to make it <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Lord;</hi> all one as Meat and Drink are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to nouriſh and keep the Body in Life. The reaſon why People do not alike in one Caſe as in the other, is, beſides that enmity againſt the Truth, which is <hi>a Root of bitterneſs ſpringing up and troubling them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many are defiled,</hi> Heb. 12. 15. Becauſe alſo they are not alike ſenſible of the neceſſity of the Truth to the ſaving of the Soul, as they are ſenſible of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Food in order to feed the Body. But when that time is come which haſteneth upon all us living, when now <hi>Meat is for the Belly and the Belly for Meats, but God ſhall deſtroy both it and them. The Graſs withereth, The Flower fadeth</hi> (and ſo all material viſible things come to an utter end, and ſhall be no more at all) <hi>but the word of our God ſhall ſtand for ever;</hi> Then ſhall ye return and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of what neceſſity the knowledge of the Truth would have been to the ſaving of your Souls, much more than ye can now diſcern in theſe Days of your fleſh; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37548:10"/> ye will then be more ſenſible of that reproof of the Spirit of God, <hi>Wherefore do you ſpend Money for that which is not Bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfieth not?</hi> Iſa. 55. 2. Wherefore do People ſpend all their Money for that Bread which was only for the ſupport of this dying Life; whereas it it is his requiring alſo that they ſhould <hi>Conſecrate their gain unto the Lord, and their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance towards the Lord of the whole Earth,</hi> Micah 4. 13. And towards the <hi>making known his Truth.</hi> Even then at the very time of receiving, it might be perceived, that the outward Bread, though indeed it did feed the Body, yet it did not ſatisfie the Soul, and ſo it was not Bread to the Soul, as it was to the Body. <hi>Man doth not live by Bread only, but by every word that proceedeth out of the Mouth of the Lord doth Man live. By the Word of God</hi> the Soul is to live eternally. <hi>This is that Bread which cometh down from Heaven, not as your Fathers did eat Manna and are Dead</hi> (and ſo they that have what can be deſired for Food and Rayment, muſt die) <hi>He that eateth of this Bread ſhall live for ever.</hi> Now we are taken up chiefly if not wholly with things ſenſible, then we ſhall be let into things Spiritual; and they will by their remaining always before us be then the whole of our Thoughts, although perhaps now it be none or the leaſt of all. It will be the Queſtion and Reproof in the ſtate of Eternity, <hi>Why People did</hi> in the Days of their Fleſh beſtow <hi>their labour for that which ſatisfieth not.</hi> The Scene will then change, things will then appear oppoſite and contrary to what they do now. <hi>O thou that dwelleſt upon many Waters, abundant in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, thine end is come and the meaſure of thy Covetouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 51. 13. Then it will appear how little it doth ſifnifie to have heaped up Riches and gotten Gain, or to have been <hi>Cumbred abovt many things,</hi> when <hi>one thing was needful</hi> and we ſhould have <hi>choſen the better part which would not have been taken from us,</hi> now all other things ſhall fail. Then alſo it will moſt eminently and clearly appear, how that Man did throughout this Life on Earth <hi>walk in a vain ſhew: And he diſquieted himſelf</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37548:11"/> 
               <hi>in vain: He heapeth up Riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is ſomewhat alike to this in <hi>Hab.</hi> 2 6. <hi>Wo to him that increaſeth that which is not his. How long? And to him that ladeth himſelf with thick clay.</hi> O that ſuch People would conſider of this, who make it their main and principal end of Life and conſume almoſt all their time in getting of Money or Riches. They know not, or are not ſenſible of as much, or at leaſt they do not take ſuch warning ſo as to refrain, how that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God doth pronounce a <hi>Wo</hi> againſt them. To Build and another ſhall Inhabit, or to Plant and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſhall eat the Fruit thereof, is according to the Curſe of God in the Book of <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> as alſo it is a Diſcouragement, Vexation and Diſquiet to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in its ſeeking and labouring thereafter. <hi>That increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that which is not his.</hi> Ay, but ſaith the Creature it is mine when I have it. To which the Anſwer of God preſently and immediately ſucceeds <hi>How long?</hi> That is, How long will it be before it is taken from thee? Or how long will it be before thou ſhall be taken from it? One Day will certainly come when it ſhall be no longer his, when he ſhall be diſlodged from this Tenement of Clay (that is, the Body) and then he can no longer lade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with <hi>thick Clay,</hi> that is, heap up Silver or Gold. Let People be never ſo much Buſied or Employed in heaping up Riches or getting Eſtates, yet the Forty Ninth Pſalm lies expreſs againſt them, <hi>For when he dieth, he ſhall carry nothing away, his Glory ſhall not deſcend after him.</hi> By reaſon that Death is to ſucceed and ſhut up all, <hi>Therefore Man walketh in a vain ſhew: Surely they are diſquieted in vain: He heapeth up Riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ask now the Generations that were before thee in the World, who are now actually gone off from the Stage of this Earth: And doth not their Life here appear to be a <hi>vain ſhew,</hi> and they ſeem to have been <hi>diſquieted in vain.</hi> As their condition is already, ſo will ours be in a very ſhort time; for we ſhall alſo die and be with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37548:11"/> them and like unto them. In one ſence that is vain which hath an end; and when that end is come, it ſeems all one as if it had never been. Exactly ſo is our Life here on Earth, for when it is ended <hi>(We bring our Years to an end as a tale that is told)</hi> it doth ſo ſeem upon the review or looking back, and ſo it will be at the end of things.</p>
            <p>Now to improve the whole foregoing Diſcourſe in wo or three Practical Uſes and Inferences.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Shall be, that we know our ſelves. The fault and errour of the reaſonable Creature is, that he ſtudies and is employed about things which are outward, but he doth not come ſo home and near to himſelf as he ſhould do. He looks too much without, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf. The Heathen did imagine that this ſaying, <hi>Know thy ſelf,</hi> did deſcend from Heaven, becauſe of the excellency of it, but chiefly becauſe it is the Mind and Will of God our Creator, that we ſhould know our ſelves, and the more we know of our ſelves, the more we know of our own vanity. It hath been ſaid, <hi>That all People will know themſelves firſt or laſt.</hi> But this is the Fault and errour of the moſt, that they come to know themſelves when it is too late. <hi>Like the Fooliſh Virgins who whilſt they went to buy, the door was ſhut,</hi> Mat. 25. 10. I have heard of one who was of a ſinful Life and Converſation, but in the time of his laſt Sickneſs did cry out, <hi>Man is vanity.</hi> But why did he not lay that to Heart in the midſt of Life and Health, when he was luſty and ſtrong? <hi>For Man even in his beſt ſtate is altogether vanity.</hi> But the thing is by ſuch perceived at the end, and not at the beginning. Whereas if it were throughly underſtood at the beginning, it would do good; but it only enhanſes the Miſery and fad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment when it is reflected upon at the end, for then it is Remedileſs.</p>
            <p>We ſhould look much within the Glaſs of our ſelves, and when we know and apprehend concerning our ſelves, we ſhould conſider much of it and remember it, and not <hi>go away and ſtraightway forgetting what manner of</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37548:12"/> 
               <hi>Men we are,</hi> James 1. 24. And when we look within our ſelves, and narrowly conſider our ſelves, we ſhould give heed to what manner of thoughts do ariſe in our Minds. If any thoughts of Pride ſhould at any time ſtart up, check them again with this conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and reaſoning; Wherefore is <hi>Duſt and Aſhes</hi> Proud? If they be concerning thine own Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Withering away, Dying and Mortality, there cheriſh them, and conſider more and more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; for ſo the holy Ghoſt wiſhes and adviſes us Mortal Men, <hi>O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end.</hi> As we are always Dying, ſo we ſhould have the continued ſenſe thereof: As we are indeed vain, ſo we ſhould have a knowledge of this our Vanity. Saith <hi>Job</hi> in his Expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to God, <hi>Wilt thou altogether look upon what is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and purſue a Leaf that is driven to and fro?</hi> Every puff of Wind doth move a Leaf; and ſo Man is like a <hi>Reed ſhaken with the Wind,</hi> of Sickneſs or ſad Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and he is liable to danger and hurt every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Each thought doth fluctuate and toſs his Soul up and down. If of good, then this is apt to lift him up. But if the thoughts be of Pain, Vexation or Evil, then this doth as much ſink and caſt him down.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughts of Man, that they are vanity,</hi> Pſal. 94. 11. For ſo they are in the eſteem of the <hi>Alwiſe God.</hi> Even ſo there may be perceived in our ſelves alſo, ſomewhat alike to this Knowledge of God. For when we conſider throughly upon what is called or ſuppoſed to be the greateſt Wiſdom of Nations, or of what are reputed wiſe Men, or even of our own beſt and greateſt Wiſdom. It doth all ſeem and appear to us but as ſilly and fooliſh in the main, or at the utmoſt it is truly vain. For the beſt Wiſdom, Contrivance and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement here is converſant only about vain things. As a Figure now differs from the thing Figured, Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from Subſtance: So all the Wiſdom that is now, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from and comes ſhort of what Wiſdom will be in the future ſtate of things, as it ſhall then reſide in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37548:12"/> Angels and Men. <hi>For the Creature was made ſubject to vanity, not willingly, but by reaſon of him that ſubjected the ſame in Hope.</hi> So that though the Creature, (by which is ſignified what is now Created) is now made ſubject to vanity; yet at this very ſame time wherein now it is under vanity, yet it is in hope to be rendred and reſtored again into a ſubſtantial and glorious ſtate. The certain Truth whereof is confirmed by the words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately following, <hi>Becauſe the Creature it ſelf alſo ſhall be delivered from the bondage of Corruption into the glorious Liberty of the Children of God.</hi> And if the Creature ſhall be <hi>delivered</hi> from Bondage into Liberty, from Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into Glory, as the Spirit here ſaith expreſly it ſhall, then alſo the Creature which is now made ſubject to vanity, ſhall at length be delivered into a ſubſtantial ſtate and being. <hi>For we know that the whole Creation groneth and travaileth in pain together until now,</hi> That is, by reaſon of the Vanity, Corruption and Bondage which is at preſent upon it. <hi>And not only they, but our ſelves alſo, which have the firſt fruits of the Spirit, even we our ſelves groan within our ſelves waiting for the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit, the Redemption of our Body. For we are ſaved by hope, but hope that is ſeen, is not hope, for what a Man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for? But if we hope for that we ſee not, then do we with patience wait for it,</hi> Rom. 8. 20. to Verſe 24. 25. Now compare theſe two laſt Verſes with <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 1. Where the Object of Faith is mentioned by that Expreſſion, <hi>Now Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for.</hi> This word, <hi>Subſtance,</hi> whereby the future things are expreſſed, is in oppoſition and contradiſtinction to that vanity, wherein all preſent things are: And not only they, but our ſelves alſo are made ſubject to this vanity: For conſider Man in his Frame and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, <hi>He is Duſt,</hi> made up of Vileneſs, Weakneſs and Mortality, walking up and down like a ſhadow, a little dependent being, a breathing clod of Clay, a moving Sink of Flegm and Excrements, a ſhapen lump of Brittle and frail Fleſh. Know thy ſelf through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truly, which the more thou doſt, the more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37548:13"/> thou wilt ſubſcribe and inwardly aſſent unto the truth of what the Spirit of God ſaith by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Surely every Man walketh in a vain ſhew: Surely they are diſquieted in vain: He heapeth up Riches and knoweth not who ſhall gather them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I would apply the foregoing Diſcourſe as to my Publiſhing the <hi>Truths of God</hi> unto the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this my Generation and Country, and as to their receiving of them. One principal Conſideration which firſt brought me acquainted with the Ways of God, was concerning the vanity of all things of this World. And there was a deſire in me, if I might ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what take off from this vanity of things by real and enduring actions. It is certain, that nothing remains in a Man but what he doth in the ſervice of God and for the good of his own Soul; and all his doings beſides that great end are vain. Which Conſideration throughly weighed ſhould inſtruct and exhort thoſe, who ſhall hear or read theſe words, to frame and bring all their doings towards this great end of ſerving God, and ſaving their Souls, or for the good of them. For whatever their Hand finds them to do beſides, is vain. Even our week day Labour in our ſeveral Callings and Occupations (which takes up moſt of our time) may be all brought under this great end. <hi>And whatſoever ye do, do it heartily as to the Lord, and not unto Men, knowing that of the Lord ye ſhall receive the reward of the Inheritance, for ye ſerve the Lord Christ,</hi> Col. 3. 23, 24. Even ſo in whatever we Labour or are Employed, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always, it be in things <hi>Lawful and Right,</hi> and in compliance with, and obedience unto that primitive Ordinance of God, <hi>In the ſweat of thy Face ſhalt thou eat Bread:</hi> It may be alſo Spiritualized and referred up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, by having our heart fixed on the inviſible God at the very ſame time, According to what <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>My heart is fixed, My heart is fixed:</hi> And ſo in our ſeveral Work and Buſineſs, in our Trade and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment we may ſerve God and Chriſt alſo. The Hu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>band-man, whilſt his Hand is upon his Plow,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37548:13"/> may have his heart upon God at the very ſame time; and then altho the <hi>Plowing of the Wicked is Sin,</hi> yet all things are good to the Godly, and this laſt Perſon even in his Plowing may and doth ſerve God. So it may be as to others; whilſt each one is handling the Tools or Inſtruments of his reſpective Trade or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, <hi>Let him lift up his heart unto God in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> and have the <hi>deſire of his Soul</hi> towards him, that he may pleaſe and find Acceptance with him, and then all along he will in his Labour ſerve the Lord; and ſo his <hi>Labour will not be in vain in the Lord:</hi> But after that he hath therein ſerved God in his Generation, he ſhall at laſt enter into the <hi>Reſt which remaineth for the People of God.</hi> Although he did meet with weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his Earthly Pilgrimage, yet abundant compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation will be made for all, <hi>When the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord,</hi> Acts 3. 19.</p>
            <p>The ſame wiſe Man, who ſaith, <hi>All is Vanity,</hi> ſaith alſo, <hi>All things are full of labour.</hi> But thus it might be ordered, even by referring it up towards God, who is the beginning and end of all things, that we may not labour in vain, but <hi>labour in hope,</hi> to come and partake of thoſe good things which the Lord God hath promiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For all People will walk every one in the Name of his God, and we will walk in the Name of the Lord our God for ever and ever,</hi> Micah. 4. 5. So it is ſeen, that though we are in a World of vain things and in the very midſt of them, yet every one is for going on in his own ways. That expreſſion is very obſervable, <hi>And</hi> Samuel <hi>ſaid into the People, Fear not, ye have done all this wickedneſs, yet turn not aſide from following the Lord, but ſerve the Lord with all your heart, and turn ye not aſide, for then ſhould ye go after vain things which cannot profit, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver for they are vain,</hi> 1 Sam. 12. 20, 21. Here it is expreſly ſaid, that if People turn aſide from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord, then they go after vain things which cannot profit nor deliver, for they are vain. But fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even in the things pertaining to God and Religion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37548:14"/> if People <hi>Walk in a way that was not good, after their own thoughts,</hi> Iſa. 65. 2. And go according to their own imaginations, and not according to the Rule and Direction of God's written Word: Here alſo they go after vain things which cannot <hi>profit,</hi> that is, not avail to the ſaving of their Souls, nor <hi>deliver</hi> from the Wrath to come, and from the fierceneſs of the Wrath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, <hi>For they are vain.</hi> And yet, how many nevertheleſs do outwardly ſerve God and mind Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only according to the thoughts of their own Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and Ignorant Heart, and they do content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves meerly with the cuſtomary Worſhip and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Religion of the multitude; although Chriſt Jeſus, who is <hi>The Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> ſaith expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Except your Righteouſneſs ſhall exceed the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> In like manner it may be truly reaſoned, Except your Religion ſhall exceed the common, cuſtomary, and outſide Religion of the multitude, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, and it will not be a Religion <hi>Unto the ſaving of the Soul.</hi> How many do even on the Lord's <hi>Holy-day</hi> ſtand in the <hi>The doors of their houſes,</hi> Ezek. 33. 30. Or ſit in the Chimny-corner, or walk in the Fields, <hi>Finding their own Pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking their own words</hi> (both which are reproved, Iſa. 58. 13.) And talking of vain things, <hi>Which cannot profit nor deliver,</hi> nor do them one jot of good as to their own Salvation, rather than they will hear or read the good Word of God, <hi>Or meditate in his Law day and night.</hi> They are like <hi>The deaf Adder that ſtoppeth her ear, which will not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the voice of Charmers, Charming never ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Pſal. 58. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Yea, even amongſt the ſeemingly Religious alſo are found thoſe who ſhew forth much Sin and Stubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt ſome part of what is in truth the Word God. <hi>But unto Iſrael he ſaith,</hi> (obſerve that word <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for it is not there ſaid unto the Heathen) <hi>All the day long have I ſtretched forth my hands unto a diſobedient and</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37548:14"/> 
               <hi>gainſaying People,</hi> Rom. 10. 21. So it is unto the Named <hi>Iſrael, (For all are not Iſrael, who are of Iſrael,</hi> Rom. 9. 6.) Unto the Profeſſors and thoſe who call themſelves Chriſtians, and not altogether to the prophane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſort he ſaith, I have ſtretched forth my hands all the Day unto a diſobedient and gainſaying People, as truly ſuch are the People of this my Generation and Country, Who reject and receive not my Miniſtry of the Word, for the ſame and alike Reaſons, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did reject and not receive the Words of Chriſt <hi>(Herein we ſhall have boldneſs in the Day of Judgment,</hi> which will be fear and ſhame and confuſion of face to them in this matter, <hi>Becauſe as he was, ſo are we in this preſent World)</hi> Namely, becauſe that in my Preaching and Writing, I have ſo learned from him my Lord and Example whoſe ſteps herein I follow, I do alſo <hi>teach the way of God in truth, neither care I for any Man, for I regard not the perſon of Men,</hi> Mat. 22. 16. For if I yet pleaſed Men, I ſhould not be the Servant of Chriſt. <hi>Wherefore holy Brethren, partakers of the heavenly Calling, conſider the Apoſtle and high Prieſt of our Profeſſion, Chriſt Jeſus. Who was faithful to him that appointed him, as alſo Moſes was faithful in all his houſe,</hi> Heb. 3. 1, 2. And ſo I do make it my ſincere and actual endeavour to be faithful to that God who appointed me to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of his Word, by his <hi>having enabled me, and given me a knowledge thereof,</hi> and by <hi>putting words into my Mouth,</hi> and ſo I make it my endeavour to be <hi>faithful</hi> in all the Miniſtration thereof. <hi>He that hath my word, let him ſpeak my word faithfully,</hi> Jer. 23. 28. <hi>Moreover it is required in Stewards, that a Man be found faithful,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 2. And becauſe I <hi>have not ſhunned to declare</hi> unto the People of this my Generation and Country, <hi>all the the counſel of God:</hi> But in the things I have written unto them, I have mentioned ſome Scriptures which other Preachers and Scribes have <hi>omitted,</hi> Mat. 23. 23. Therefore they reject and receive not that part of the Word of God which hath been committed to my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, <hi>Speaking evil of me;</hi> Who for this their falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37548:15"/> and <hi>Partiality, Mal.</hi> 2. 9. Stubbornneſs and Rebellion, <hi>ſhall give account to him that is ready to judge the quick and the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Seeing that all things here on Earth are vain, and Man the chief inhabitant thereof walketh in a <hi>vain ſhew,</hi> How ſhould this Knit and Unite our Hearts up unto God himſelf, and alſo towards the future ſtate of things, for all there is Reality and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. God himſelf is the moſt real and ſubſtantial being that can be, for he created all things, and now upholds them by the Word of his Power. If any thing is real, God himſelf is much more ſo; and ſo likewiſe are all the things pertaining to his Kingdom in Heaven. <hi>The Creature was made ſubject to vanity.</hi> God made all things on this Earth ſo vain, to the intent to draw off our Deſires and Affections yet more from the things of this World, to fix and ſet them on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the things above, that in our earneſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeeking after Earthly things (they are <hi>Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, who mind Earthly things)</hi> we may meet with this kind of Check and Reproof from our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>O ye Sons of Men, How long will ye turn my Glory into ſhame, how long will ye love vanity and ſeek after lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? Selah</hi> Pſal. 4. 2. Importing, that whilſt the Sons of Men do love vanity and ſeek after leaſing, <hi>So long they turn the glory of God into ſhame:</hi> In that hereby they do quite pervert the very deſign and order of things. For whereas God deſigned his own Glory in making Man a reaſonable Creature, that is, one capable to ſeek after himſelf, and the things of the other and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter World; <hi>But by loving vanity and ſeeking after leaſing,</hi> Man doth degenerate himſelf, <hi>And being made in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he abideth not.</hi> When it would be for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory of God if he did purſue the right end, but by not doing or intending that, he doth properly <hi>turn the Glory of God into ſhame.</hi> For it would be a ſhame if an alwiſe God ſhould make reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creatures for no better and higher an end than to <hi>love vanity and ſeek after leaſing:</hi> Whereas here the fault
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37548:15"/> is in the Creatures themſelves, and in no wiſe in God who Created them. In like manner, every act of Sin doth <hi>turn the Glory of God into ſhame</hi> for the ſame Reaſon, becauſe it is a perverting of things from what he firſt made and deſigned them; for he Created Man to ſerve God and do Good, and not that he ſhould Corrupt himſelf by committing Sin and Evil, or by <hi>loving vanity and ſeeking after leaſing.</hi> Vanity is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto the Lord as Sin and Evil is. For this is the Will of God, even your Sanctification, that not ſo much as <hi>Vain thoughts ſhould lodge within ye,</hi> Jer. 4. 14. And that People ſhould not <hi>ſpeak vanity,</hi> Pſal. 12. 2. <hi>nor truſt in vanity,</hi> Iſa. 59. 4. Much leſs commit or do the ſame. But as we are commanded, <hi>Not to touch the unclean thing,</hi> So we are to refrain from all vain things as much as it is poſſible to do in this vain World which paſſeth away. According to the Exhortation which ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on this wiſe, <hi>If ye then be riſen in Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth on the Right hand of God. Set your affection on things above, not on things on the Earth. For ye are Dead, and your Life is hid with Chriſt in God: When Chriſt, who is our Life ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo appear with him in Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved, when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common Salvation, it was needful for me to write unto you, and exhort you, and put you in mind of the vanity of all things of this World, that People ſhould not forſake God and depart from the Faith once delivered to the Saints, nor go aſide from the Truth, out of Love to this preſent World, but that ye ſhould Love God more and the World not at all. <hi>For if any Man loveth the World, the love of the Father is not in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>So Witneſſeth and Exhorteth <signed>RICHARD STAFFORD, a Scribe inſtructed in the Law of God, and in the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:37548:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1700. And are to be Sold unto ſuch who will <hi>receive the love of Truth that they might be Saved.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:37548:16"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THeſe are to give notice, That I have ſeveral other Practical Sermons or Diſcourſes of mine own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing lying by me in Manuſcript: Which if they who have the Plenty or Competency of this World's Goods, would <hi>(According to their ſeveral Ability,</hi> Acts 11. 29.) Thus <hi>Conſecrate ſome part of their gain and ſubſtance unto the Lord,</hi> Micah 4. 13. So as to be <hi>ready to diſtribute, and willing to Communicate</hi> towards the outward Labour and Charge of the Printing and Publiſhing of them, it would be for the Glory of God <hi>(in making known his Truth,</hi> Iſa. 38. 19.) And for the Edification and Benefit of his Church and People; and conſequently it would be a Good work in ſuch Perſons who ſhall be helpful and any ways aſſiſtant herein, for which they would be rewarded by God in the Life that is to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I ſay unto you, Make to your ſelves Friends of the</hi> Mammon <hi>of unrighteouſneſs; that when ye fail, they may receive you into Everlaſting Habitations,</hi> Luke 16. 9. <hi>Charge them that are rich in this World, that they do Good, that they be Rich in Good Works, ready to Diſtribute, willing to Communicate, laying up in Store for themſelves a good Foundation againſt tbe time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 17. 18. 19. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and theſe things I will that thou affirm conſtantly, that they which have believed in God, might be careful to maintain Good Works; theſe things are Good and Profitablſi unto Men,</hi> Titus 3. 8.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
